howdy this is jim rutt and this is the
jim rutt show
listeners have asked us to provide
pointers some of the resources we talk
about on the show
we now have links to books and articles
referenced in recent podcasts that are
available on our website
we also offer full transcripts go to
jimrutshow.com
that's jimrutsshow.com
unfortunately we had some technical
issues while recording this episode and
the sound quality isn't up to our
usual standards nonetheless it's very
listenable and the content
is great today's guest
is daniel christian wall and this is
part two a continuation of an episode
we recorded back in february ep 43
episode 43 you can find it with a google
just googled jim rutcho ep ep43
daniel is a leader in thought and action
in catalyzing transformative innovation
cultural co-creation whole systems
design
and bioregional regeneration
he is the author of designing
regenerative cultures which i read in
preparation for today's episode
he lives in mallorca spain as always
there's links to that book and any other
books or
organizations or papers that we
reference uh
in the episode today and they're
available on the episode page at
jimrutshow.com other interesting thing
about
daniel's background is he lived in the
finned horn eco village i believe that
was in scotland is that right
yeah far north of scotland yeah and he
was the director of the finn horne
college and i have one little
odd uh personal relationship with the
finn horn
tradition and that is uh i don't know
many years ago 25
30 years ago we had a good friend peg
shadler hi peg if you're out there
look us up my wife and i were friends
with her and her husband and her kids
and
she was a finned horn follower and i was
i'm a deer hunter still am
and she requested that if i killed a
buck could i save the bladder for her
apparently stagg's bladders uh were part
of the
finned horn style agriculture at least
so she said
so that was my one relationship to kind
of the finn horned thing
that sounds like biodynamic agriculture
actually which is
used in finton quite a lot um but they
do things like mixing those kind of
things up
in in a bull's horn and then you you
stir it
umpteen times clockwise and umpteen
times anti-clockwise
in the full moon and you bury those
horns in the different corners of the
field
and well certainly won't put our
analytical scientists to
prove that one right but their produce
is wonderful
and they swear by it and it seems to be
working yeah okay
of course i was highly skeptical being a
rational scientific sort but heck if you
know she won the stag bladder i gave her
a stag bladder and she had one of the
most beautiful gardens i know anywhere
so
anyway good to hear your voice again
it's already picking me up despite the
fact that we've got
39 degrees centigrade here on mallorca
and it's a really hot afternoon so
ah yeah that's it i'm thinking slowly
no problem uh and yeah and you know some
interesting things in my life too
our first granddaughter just arrived a
couple of days ago
and uh you know wow maybe that's why i
have a good energized
sound today because looking at that
beautiful tiny baby who had no
doings in creating this messed up world
we live in
just made it all much more real to me
about the
importance of the work that you're doing
work i'm doing work lots of people we
know are doing
to try to save the world god damn it
right
we got to do it yeah saving ourselves is
probably more what we're doing because
the process is going to keep going um
even without us but it would be a very
much
impoverished planet even if only our
species would power out
center stage left but in the process
we're probably going to take a hell of a
lot of other species with us so yeah
let's let's do the good work
yeah exactly and uh yeah in fact i think
you said we are a capstone species
capable of creating conditions
conducive to all life we can design for
human
ecosystems and planetary health nurture
resilience adaptability transformability
and
vitality which really resonated with me
because recently i've discovered a new
thinker
named tyson juncka porta he has a
amazing book out called sand talk i've
had him on the
podcast three times and he talks about
humans as the custodial species and i
think
that concept and your concept of the
capstone species are very very similar
and that yes you're absolutely right a
life
without humans is quite different and
maybe in a huge
fundamental way than a universe with
humans and we'll talk about that in some
detail when we get later in the talk
yeah i just want to say briefly about
tyson young like he's been on my radar
for for a while and i still haven't read
his
book and then um you've done three
conversations with him in a relatively
short period of time
and i really want to read his book and
learn more about him because
in the last year year and a half i've
had a number of conversations with maori
and aboriginally
ancestral wisdom carriers and
the resonance is striking and it's
if you i should send you the link to a
conversation i have with a guy called
johnny freeland
from new zealand who's part of the
regenerative development network
in in auckland and um the conversation
is about
square and circular systems thinking and
i think you'd enjoy having him on your
show at some point as well
yeah that'd be great really good you
know and tyson
it you know provides a very interesting
we talk about this in the first episode
double perspective uh one is his
indigenous
australian tribal indigenous people's
perspective and then he's also been a
student of complexity science
and the way he blends those two without
offending either is quite remarkable i
mean
this book is a major work of art as well
it's not straightforward
it's not linear it weaves it brings in
all kinds of
curious things but you know read that
damn book it's good
now before we dig into new material i do
think it's helpful to recap
three of the big ideas that we talked
about last time so people
can have some grounding without having
to go back and read the previous episode
so first daniel if you would if you
could talk a little bit about the
difference
and the overlap of course and one
probably includes the other
uh the difference between the
regenerative perspective versus a
sustainable perspective
well you'll get different answers from
different people when you when you ask
that question but
in my perspective i see it as part of a
spectrum
that goes from business as usual to
doing things a little bit better which
is green
um to getting to that point where
sustainable is defined of having
no negative impact um of whatever you do
you don't add to the problem but the
the problem is that we've been adding to
the problem for hundreds of years
with increasing impact and now what we
need to do is to actually go beyond that
and
restore the damage we've done and
working regeneratively
goes beyond all of that in the sense
that
we really begin to re-identify with life
as a planetary evolutionary process
us ourselves as participants in nested
complexity
and we we ask ourselves the question how
do we participate
appropriately in that nested complexity
to increase its health wholeness
vitality and capability to keep
evolving into an uncertain and
uncontrollable future and so working
regeneratively is always working
developmentally and in with an
evolutionary mindset so you you
it's more important to build the
capacity of people
to keep on evolving and keep on
responding to change and adapting and
transforming
then to lock down on a specific solution
and then pretend that once we've got the
right blueprint in place
everything will be happy ever after that
makes
good sense uh another important idea
that's in your book and again i would
highly recommend people read
daniel's book designing regenerative
cultures is the concept of three
horizons which you credit to
bill sharp i think and a couple of
others could you tell us about the three
horizons and
you know what they are and where you
think we are on that transition
well first maybe to highlight because
sometimes people fall into that trap
um mckinsey brought out a very basic
three horizons
model in the late 90s and so don't
confuse it with that
three horizon model it's a very
different one
and it was developed within the
international futures forum
the book three horizons a patterning of
hope was written by
my friend bill sharp and he's really the
one who's kind of
dedicated the last 10 years to really
get this practice more widely recognized
than out there because
after many decades in um technology
futures and foresight work
bill realized that we needed a more
agile
and open framework to converse about
possible futures um and that even the
kind of classic scenario planning for
scenario framework was limited and and
not not agile enough
and in a nutshell three horizons allows
us to do is to have this
to some extent to frame it
regeneratively it's
working with the opposing forces of on
the one hand the perspective that is
needing to keep business as usual
running so the the the manager or the
political
um politician in charge having to keep
the lights on people in schools people
and jobs all of that
and that's called horizon one that's
business as usual
and then in on the opposing end you have
horizon three
the new viable future that
right now is only existing in in pockets
and is often seen as the visionary
transformative aspect where
that horizon one can't fully connect
with and normally you get the
head butting between the visionaries and
and the managers
and by introducing horizon two which is
um disruptive innovation innovation
entrepreneurship as a bridge that
can help us to really have the
conversation of what
do we still need to keep from
business as usual from horizon one what
is it that is already present in the
available in the in the present
examples that are the examples of
pockets of the future in the present
that we
are in the long term building but what
are the stepping stone innovations that
are possible today and economically
feasible today that we can get
engaged with right now in the second
horizon space and then focus in on that
space
as the potential bridge building towards
enabling the third horizon and in that
space you can then ask
what innovation is a horizon two minus
meaning um something that will just
prolong business as usual and will be
captured by horizon one
and what is the horizon two plus a a
true stepping stone towards
the the viable regenerative
transformative future and
that's it in a nutshell but ultimately
one sentence i really like by bill sharp
that he often uses when he facilitates
with it is that
it's not necessarily going to make
everybody agree on what to do
um immediately after you facilitate a
conversation with this framework
but what you do create is an environment
where everybody can
disagree much more intelligently and has
developed future consciousness in a
really agile
quick way that allows them then to talk
about
the sequence of what to do when in in
a completely new way and i've seen it
work in in many contexts and i've
co-facilitated with bill and
it's yeah it's a very useful tool yeah i
like it a lot and it's you know it's
realistic one you know my
in my life as a business person one of
the things i was always
aware of i used to use the language you
can't jump
up a cliff right if someone comes to you
with a business idea that
goes a to b straight up a cliff the
probability of that succeeding is off
almost zero one has to think about how
do you find a
a slope to climb up the hill rather than
to jump up a thousand foot cliff
and you know this this kind of thinking
strikes me as very congruent with that
it's also congruent with our game b
theories we talk about game a which we
can call a world in crisis
and true game b a viable meta-stable
world
and then we talk about transition be
which is the uh
the world between the two so i think uh
we're all pretty much on the same page
there
yeah and it's it's really being used in
a lot of powerfully transformative
contexts so so bill's
kind of got in with an organization
called leaders quest
a number of years ago because because
they
realize the the usefulness of this tool
and
we're asking him to train up their
facilitators when they take out
c-level business leaders to to kind of
extreme environments like
talking to people on death row or
spending a couple of days in a slum in
mumbai and then they they kind of post
process and
and and create transformative insights
for people and over time
that partnership has grown into work
with an organization called futures
stewards that is now collaborating with
ted and with
um youtube and they're creating a
process called
countdown which is really trying to
engage both business and civil society
much more deeply in the
cop conversation and the climate change
agenda
and builds basic set of
conversation facilitation tools that
he's developing in that including
three horizons is is kind of the
backbone of
a lot of well what they're developing
now to to sort of
engage people with the climate agenda in
a new way
using ted and and youtube actively
interesting these are great big picture
things i'm going to
jump down to a very sharp detail a very
uh
micro detail something i happen to be
very interested in
from your book you quote from the rodale
institute
regenerative organic agriculture is
marked by tendencies towards closed
nutrient loops underlying that one
great diversity in the biological
community fewer fewer annuals more
perennials
and greater reliance on internal rather
than external resources i'm going to
underline that last piece too
internal rather than external resources
so closed nutrient loops and internal
rather than external
which brings me up to one of my pet
topics
which is the use of night soil in
organic farming
not done at all in the united states in
fact it's illegal under most
circumstances
night soil meaning human solid waste
also known as
right a huge amount of uh nitrogen and
other nutrients
are in night soil and they it's been
used through all of human history and
local agriculture still used regularly
in
east asia and yet in the west it's not
and i don't see how we can have closed
nutrient loops
and rely on internal rather than
external resources
until we get over our squeamishness and
learn how to
reprocess our night soil our
back into our soils i i would agree and
we can get really geeky on this
uh watch out what kind of conversation
you open up
on the small scale of course there is
absolute at the farm scale then the
recycling of nutrients immediately makes
so much sense in in that environment
when you go to urban
scale it's a little bit more tricky
because it depends on like if you know
who's been basically relieving
themselves
in your compost toilet or in your
aquatron that's
separate solids from from liquids it's a
swedish invention
then then you know the quality of the
pool you've got but if you
look at the city um if people have been
treating themselves with antibiotics and
all sorts of other legal or illegal
drugs all of that
can also bioaccumulate in the soil so so
with with urban environments it it makes
sense to go through a
more complex composting process to close
the nutrient loop but it makes absolute
sense to do so but one one example that
i found always
fantastic is friends of mine at the
center for alternative technology in
wales who've been working on these
things for 40 years
more than that actually 50 years now
they
were instrumental in setting up in the
david valley a
community supported agriculture scheme
where people would basically buy in a
share
in their local farm and then they get a
veg box delivered
depending on on the harvest at the time
so you you kind of share in
rather than just a veg box scheme where
you can stop it anytime
you actually share the risk over the
whole year and you commit to your pharma
for the whole year and that way they can
calculate the risk of agriculture much
better and
as part of this particular vegbox scheme
or csa scheme was that when
they brought the vegetables to people's
doors they would take a big
container of yellow liquid back to the
fields which is the
rich nitrogen that people were peeing
out from having eaten all that
food so they they were really literally
closing the loops in that practical way
with their committed community and
that's possible but but it's probably
not a mainstream solution for
the streets of new york or wherever
but on the other hand a friend of mine
actually was the superintendent for a
the waste treatment center at a city of
about a hundred thousand people medium
size
and they ran a large scale experiment
using a process
to create a fertilizer called
malorganite which basically took
urban sludge got rid of the antibiotics
got rid of the heavy metals i don't
remember the details of the process
and then they gave the malorganite away
free to everybody in the county who
wanted to come and get it
and that was quite interesting that's
what we're doing here on mayoka like in
mallorca the sludge from the sewage
treatment plants gets
dried in kind of racks with concentrated
sunlight and then that really baked
material gets um put into the compost
composting and then the compost is free
to people to to get and put back on
their fields
so ultimately we are cycling human waste
on majorca as well
yeah i just i always hit this again
because i think in terms of cycles right
as a systems thinker
and i go wait a minute if we're not
recycling this very concentrated source
of nutrients
then there's no effing way we're going
to be able to be long-term sustainable
especially not with a population of 10
billion people
particularly if we you know have
committed to not degrade mother nature
any further so
i just like to underscore this that i at
least
can't take organic farming seriously as
a solution to the world's problems until
we
agree to solve this problem which is to
recycle these nutrients
yeah we i think we're all somewhat
oblivious to the fact of how important
phosphorus is to the future of our
civilization and and human life on earth
um
and phosphorus is a tricky one and to
like even
like i was talking to the the local
traditional pharmacy on the island and
asked them sort of
do you remember what did your great
great grandfather import
and the one thing that they imported
even back then was phosphorus
and and so yes absolutely true we need
to
make sure that we keep that on the land
yep you're exactly right phosphorus is
probably the limiting factor
of uh life on earth period right i think
i remember as a kid reading an article
by isaac asimov who calculated that
all the phosphorus in the crust of the
earth was only enough to support about
six trillion people something like that
and in reality
the limits are way way lower than that
in fact i've seen some arguments that
say we've already exceeded the bounds of
phosphorus
extraction from the earth and unless we
get this recycling all the way around
of our wastes we may be in a deeply
depletive role on at least the easily
accessible phosphorus right now
i work with an organization called the
international futures forum and
there's a wonderful man who used to be
kind of the
future scanning lead for hewlett packard
for many years
um ian page and since he retired quite a
few years ago he's
been in the mountains in wales just
researching every day
day in day out on a project which he
calls chon
carbon oxygen hydrogen and nitrogen and
this is
a project that after working his way
through the entire periodic table
and looking at the depletion curves of
all the elements in it
he just concluded that if we want to
have
this idea of a ongoing human
civilization actually get to the point
of calling us
like being civil enough to call
ourselves a civilization
we need to basically reinvent our
material culture
to be entirely driven by renewable
energy
and dependent on those four elements
that
nature recycles freely i mean you can
have a few more trace elements of other
relatively abundant ones but everything
else is going to run out sooner or later
and now that we have to make such a
massive transition if we keep that
long-term view in mind
then it would make entirely sense to if
as we redesign everything now to really
look at
a chon material system and that is
renewable space because otherwise we'll
we'll
design a system that in 250 300 500
years
we have to redesign again might as well
get clear that there's there's a hint in
the word non-renewable resource
it will eventually run out indeed and
that is the transition that we all have
to make right
deeply and personally and
institutionally
and so now let's let's move to the
personal side this is something we
didn't talk about
as much in the first episode and this is
a fairly long quote from your book
in regenerative cultures personal
development and the evolution of
consciousness will accelerate as we
cease to be paralyzed
by the fear-driven cycle of separation
scarcity and the struggle for control
and power will begin to unfold the
potential
of a compassionate empathetic
collaborative culture of creativity
and shared abundance driven by biophilia
our innate love for all of life the
narrative of separation from the rest of
life and
alienation from nature's wisdom is
beginning to give way to a narrative
that celebrates our communion with
nature
as the very essence of our being
yeah that's been wordy isn't it yeah but
it's great i mean it says it all that's
why
i normally don't take quotes that long
but i i looked at places to cut it
and it wasn't all there unless they gave
the whole thing
yeah it's i think it's part of my german
heritage the germans love
making these really long sentences and
then they put the verb at the end
so you really have to build your
capacity to sort of hold it in suspense
until you know what's what's coming
but yeah what that paragraph
tries to describe in very western
long-winded ways is basically
i i believe what um tyson jacob porter
speaks about
so this is not some sort of oh now we
need to evolve to
a completely well we need to
move forward rather than backward that's
for sure but but there has
that kind of wisdom has been around for
most of our species existence
in many different ways whether it's in
australia in south africa
south america or africa or many other
places
yeah i think that's right and i i will
confess personally to having become
more aware of the personal
operating system level changes that are
necessary
coming from a sort of scientific realist
materialist perspective
you know i think i was a little
blinkered on realizing how important
you know even if sticking with a
materialist realist perspective
that the operating system in the agents
matters a whole lot on what's
capable of being developed in the
culture right
and so you know part of this mission
that we're all on to
you know create a what comes next which
is truly sustainable and
frankly better for everybody you know i
become much
more interested and aware of the
importance
of what people call expanded
consciousness
or spirituality people who listen to the
show know that i don't like the word
spirituality
uh call it the s word but i've come to
understand that at least
some meanings of it uh are important and
good
and that you know people do have to
reach
this new point where they understand
that we live in a constrained world and
that there are other forms of
richness rather than accumulating
stuff and so we have to really uh think
clearly about this
and and we have to co-evolve uh our
institutions and our systems on one side
but with the operating system of the
humans or what we might call
consciousness higher consciousness etc
well it's it's interesting because you
can really reframe frame this whole
conversation in
scientific terms but not necessarily if
you follow the dogma that
western science is the only science that
then qualifies for that game because
really the vedanta and many other
sciences
of the past have a very different take
and
even if you think of it in terms of
western science
the explanatory models that western
science had to
really speak about complexity or even
what we were finding out in physics at
the beginning of the last century
and weren't enough so what happens is
that all these geniuses of physics
around that time turned towards the east
and the vedanta and
and vedic sciences in order to explain
what they were bumping up against and
it's really
um like i just recently had a
conversation with with elizabeth
sartorius who was a evolutionary
biologist and she she puts it in
quite interesting terms of saying it's a
keyboard
and you can either start with the low
notes which is
um stuff evolving out of mata and
eventually there's life and then there's
emergence and oh there's consciousness
or you can start at the high notes of
the keyboard
where the the axiom of that science the
fundamental pre
supposition that that science is based
on is that everything is conscious
and everything is alive and and there
are lots of scientists who've been
operating from that even
islamic sciences when they were asked to
write down their fundamental axioms
axiom number one was allah created the
world the living world
and axiom number two was he told us to
study it
so so what i'm what i'm getting at is
that we need to be a little less
dogmatic
in terms of what we accept
as part of the scientific discussion
suddenly we see that
out of the acceptance of multiple ways
of knowing
approaching that subject there's a huge
amount of overlap
yeah though i'm going to push back a
little bit here and you know people
listen to
the show know that this is something i
do a little bit on this particular topic
and that i find it uh worrisome if we
talk about
vedantic science or islamic science
because they're not really science i
mean science is
a specific way of knowing that has
a engine inside of it where people
create hypotheses they do experiments
they look at data
and this is the key that they
collectively in an intersubjective
and inter-objective way verify or
refute hypothesis with reproducible
data or experiment and that is a
fundamentally different and i would
argue in most cases
better way of actually moving towards
real solid knowledge the other systems
of the world up to that point including
quasi-scientific thinkers like aristobal
or thomas aquinas
were still in what i call wisdom
traditions
which are frankly to my mind very
similar to
great literature they certainly have
some deep insights
that are worth thinking about and that's
why it's so useful for
physicists trying to wrestle with what
the hell is quantum mechanics in 1922
right that's such a weird concept
it's very useful for them to look at
some particularly the eastern traditions
because there's essentially the
equivalent of literature kind of deep
reaches to you know things beyond what
we can know in a solid fashion but they
aren't
actually science and so but this is
exactly the conversation where we
actually i mean yes
there's a lot of bs in that field
and a lot of bizarre kind of on the one
hand
critiquing science and then using
science to build credibility in a in the
sort of
spiritual seeker field um i i dislike
that kind of energy
myself and ultimately science is an
inter-subjective consensus-making
activity that is based on agreement of a
certain
methodology and certain axioms and then
from there we can build so basically if
we follow these axioms and we follow
this methodology then we can
observe something that is actually that
we can
create inter-subjective consensus about
and then if we repeat it we can have a
similar
result to verify whether our consensus
makes sense and in that loose framing
i think you you can say that there have
been
in many traditions rigorous study of how
the world
works and also it's that the one
even within science there's a point
where
with the newtonian universe the ways of
knowing collapse
down to just thinking and analytical
thinking and
particularly the world as it can be
expressed in the kind of languages
that are used in western cultures
western languages which are very
different from the pictographic
languages
and the kind of space of consciousness
space that that a chinese
um like a kanji alphabet or
a mandarin alphabet offer and and so
and goethe for example was was very
keenly aware that
we were going down in research science
200 years ago a tract that was not
paying attention to qualities and was
only paying attention to what is
quantifiable
and analytically um or statistically
significant
like basically quantifiable in one way
or another
turned into turnable into mathematics
and that's a it's a very
wonderful powerful tool as we know
but it's not the only way of creating
meaning meaningful and empirically
testable
knowledge about the world i believe yeah
and i think there's
and this is you know again you've said
no newtonian and i agree with you and i
push back a lot against what i call
newtonian naivete
right and i was guilty of it as a nerdy
14 year old i
probably believe laplace's conjecture
that
you know tell me the uh position and
motion of every particle in the universe
and i can predict all of history
uh and yet we've come to know you know a
deeper knowledge of science and
and i guess this is where i react
negatively to some framings
of science isn't enough because yes
newtonian naive newtonianism
of a 14 year old nerds perspective is
not enough but the world has moved on
since that
time as you mentioned earlier early in
the 20th century
we first had special relativity and then
we had
general relativity which you know twists
the hell out of the
newtonian perspective particularly once
you really understand what they're
saying they say some really
non-intuitive things and yet they're
clearly true and then
even more so quantum mechanics which we
still don't
really understand how to interpret in
ways that you know make intuitive sense
to us and yet they also
at least at a measurements perspective
have a large amount of truth to them
and then we move into the area where
i've been working the last 20 years in
complexity science
where things can't necessarily be
quantified
and in fact we know and we can prove
that you can't quantify them
deterministic chaos which says that even
in a newtonian universe
tiny tiny tiny differences below our
level to measure can make gigantic
differences on future trajectories
so when you allow science to grow to
include these
bigger perspectives and science is an
engine that grows and adds to its
toolkit
i think it can it can absorb these
things that you know that are useful and
reproducible as you say if it's
reproducible
if you can state it as a hypothesis and
you can reproduce it objectively
then it's science no matter what the the
content is
i i mean i'm i'm deeply influenced by
through my
like my connection with professor brian
goodwin at schumacher college
and all the wisdom that i learned from
him about
complexity theory um has has
significantly shaped my world view
goethe coming back together briefly said
supposedly the the history of science is
science itself and
coined this term called the historicity
of science
and part of the problem is that if we
were really open and didn't have a dogma
of where to put the lens of science then
we could study
like like like for example the the
battle that
paul stamets has been fighting to just
put more
effort into researching how the fungi
kingdom
holds so many keys towards
earth custodianship or earth stewardship
or healing the land
um so we we very often they're just
certain areas of science where we're not
putting the emphasis
and the research in while the science
that is beholden to
technological quick fix solutions that
just offer
solutions to problems we've created
because we're using
mistaken technologies is where most of
the research goes
so my my question is is if we if we did
science more daringly in the areas where
we needed
wonderful and i'm absolutely not against
science at all i'm just
open to other ways of knowing and
holding
the perspectives that different lenses
on the world give us
lightly enough that we can learn from
their point of intersection i agree that
they make a final distinction then we'll
move on the things you talked about you
know we're
not necessarily looking in the right
places our priorities aren't right in
science etc
and you're you're referencing the
mycenium the uh
amazing fungal networks which we are
learning rapidly are
amazingly interesting uh that unify
uh the the soil and our plant worlds in
ways we had no idea 15 years ago
but and this is the point about science
we are now investigating that
and so i would make a distinction and
this is something i've been trying to
make clear to people in these kinds of
discussions
is that yes the sociology of science
definitely needs a lot of tuning you
know how is funding done what is a
career who is a scientist
what is the basis by which we do
inter-subjective verification
currently it's peer-reviewed journals is
that correct all those things need a lot
of work
but the inner engine of science itself
whether you take a properion model
or other exact models of how we go from
hypothesis to a tentative
truth and always remember it's a
tentative truth if a scientist says if
someone says
science says this is true they're not a
scientist right because
science truths are always tentative you
know make that distinction between that
sociology of science which frames what
questions who's a scientist etc
with the actual engine of how we do
science and i think
it makes a lot more sense uh that the
the engine
i can't find a problem with and but the
sociology there's
a lot of ways to improve so you know i
just want to make that last one and i'm
going to push back on another one just
happens to be one of my pet peeves
because it's something i studied
you talked about mandarin and pictograph
uh versus alphabetic
i don't think that's likely to be true
and here's why as we've learned more
about the neurocognitive science
of literacy and i would point people to
stanislaus
de haney a french cognitive
neuroscientist
who's written a great book on the
neuroscience of reading
it turns out that when we go from
alphabet or pictograph to our language
processing
it runs through our audio system first
so
there's a simple or you know there's a
relatively simple mapping from
the representation to a sound in our
head and we use the same
sound in our head to process language
when we're reading
as we do when we're talking so i've
heard this argument before i've got a
friend of mine who i argue with about it
all the time
but i would say i don't buy the
pictograph
versus alphabet distinction is likely to
have any huge significance in our
cognition
on the other hand there is the safer
wharf hypothesis
which says that any difference in
language irrespective of how it's
represented
in writing may well change how we think
about the world you know the famous
example is you know the eskimos have
that's precisely that's precisely the
meeting point of consciousness in
science that
that or william blake was speaking to
when when he said
um may goddess keep from single vision
and newton's sleep um oh god he used the
god word and you're going to push back
on that one then but but it's paying
attention
to the cognitive dimension
of perception and how our organizing
ideas
and the the language and the words we
use and the frameworks we use actually
are part
of how we bring forth the world so in
terms of science language is
involving the second and the third level
observer reflecting
on every entry into how are we doing
science
and how are we reflecting on science
it's first order second order and third
or science or the science
in the language of some people yeah i
think that again as i said that at least
i i make at least two levels of
distinction one is the inner engine
and then there's the sociology which is
how do we actually do it
in practice driven by all the biases and
stupidities and limitations of actual
humans right which can of course
be approved but let's move on to some
other topics here
you know this is one we we touched upon
but i think in
talking about the mind and spirit etc
in uh last episode we talked a little
bit about the hedonistic treadmill
and status through things and positional
goods
and and that's really in some ways the
engine which is driving game a
or the you know the critical crisis that
we're in the first horizon
what do you think about what can replace
that because
certainly humans have to be satisfied
right there has to be something that
satisfies them in their living and
draws them to do good things in the
world whether it's the work that they do
whether it's the social
contributions they make to their
communities and that are families
what is it that we can replace the
hedonistic treadmill with
i think it's it's terribly exasperated
and driven
by energized by marketing media
the storytelling we have and it goes
back a long long time the narrative
about our culture and what is worth
pursuing
and even how we then structured entire
institutions and education and so on and
so forth
um around that that it's it's not so
easy to detangle
ourselves from all these past design
decisions
that are now reinforcing that kind of
competitive hedonistic pursuit framework
but
if we really look at the evolution of
our species
we can see how important collaboration
um has been
and even throughout evolution
collaboration has had a much more
important
role than our storytelling tends to
allow for
and so i think that if we
again in terms of the regenesis or
um carl sanford potential and
essence-focused approach
to regenerative development the way that
we can all
fully express our uniqueness each and
every one of us
has unique gifts to share to the benefit
of the whole
and in doing so optimizes their
potential
at the maximum creating cultures around
the experience that makes people realize
serving the community serving the local
ecosystem
serving the healing of the planet in a
time
where we all get enough lessons how
fragile
the current life support system has
become
on on planet earth i think we we are
beginning
already to to create these new
narratives and discover
that these were the guiding narratives
that many cultures had for
millennia to guide appropriate
participation within limits
in in the places that they were
inhabiting
so i've noticed and you mentioned finton
earlier i spent four years living in
in a intentional community that was sort
of experimenting with new ways of living
together
and there is a wealth that comes from
like i often reflected on the fact
walking around what was called the field
of dreams that were
lots of people had bought a plot built a
house but it was part of the community
there were no god
no fences and so on walking around the
whole place
with the wind farm on the horizon and
and the forest and the gardens and all
the infrastructure
i had a sense of ownership despite the
fact that i didn't own any of it
and the connection with the people was
even if you didn't speak a kind of level
of understanding and
and mutual holding in everybody's
journey to
give the best they can to the community
i
i actually think that that's a narrative
that that people are yearning for
because there's a there's a lot of
uh lack of meaning in that hedonistic
pursuit
story like um joseph campbell famously
said
getting to the top of the ladder and
realizing that it's leaning against the
wrong wall
and i i know a lot of people that that
have had
rather shocking experiences in their
life where they got to the top of a
big corporation or their career game and
then in their mid 40s realized that that
wasn't really
fulfilling them either that's my life
story pretty much you know i made it to
the top i was ceo of a good-sized
publicly traded company
and at the age of 47 i said all
that basically
it didn't didn't really do anything for
me anymore and i said it's a life that's
a mile wide and an inch deep
right where's the depth you know some
language i've been using lately i've
discovered it actually
i used to argue that the game b movement
our goal ought to be self-actualization
from abraham maslow's
hierarchy of values but then somebody
challenged me on that
fairly recently and said ah well that's
part of it rut but you're missing an
important part and i had a
good conversation with them and i
realized they were absolutely right so
i've reformulated it as
follows that yes we need to
self-actualize so that we reach
who we can be to make ourselves
better people right and accomplish what
we can accomplish however
that has to be in the context of
community actualization
right because we are deeply social
animals as you've pointed out many times
and as many other people have pointed
out
now let's turn that around and say the
point of community
actualization is to create a self-act to
increase our capability for
self-actualization
which increases our capability for
community actualization
as a virtuous circle this is precisely
as far as i understand it i'm not in
this group but i i think that
the um change agents development group
that carol sanford is running with a lot
of people who are part of the
regenerative movement
is basically creating a forum in which
people can engage
in providing for each other the
community in which
you keep checking that we're constantly
in this journey
of paying attention to our
reading of the world and how we process
our reading of the world
and how we develop ourselves and our
capability to fully respond
to the situation in a way that we can
bring
our essence our unique contribution to
the situation
and it's it's it has this idea of nested
complexity of
of the only way that you can really
serve yourself
is serving the the next larger hole that
you're
engaged with and that that sounds very
akin to what you were describing to my
mind yeah
the only slight nuance is that the
community has to have as one of its main
goals in its operating system helping
each individual self-actualize as well
so it's a you know it's a cycle
community
activation and actualization produces
self-actualization which increases
community actualization so you have this
virtual circle dynamic that is
essentially pumping itself up to higher
and higher levels of actualization
at both at two levels simultaneously the
self
and the community i've really come to
like that idea
but let's move on to another topic my
good friend jordan hall
who i've been working with for many
years on topics of this sort
has very recently put forth an idea
called sivium
you can uh google it i think he's got
four or five or six
uh youtube videos on it where he
started off with some ideas from the
santa fe institute from jeffrey west and
louise bettencourt
where they've done some very interesting
work on what they call the super
linearity of
cities uh to drop back a little bit
jeffrey west in particular with a couple
of collaborators the santa fe institute
has done a lot of work on the scaling
laws
of life and it turns out that for
animals the scaling law
is about three-quarters which means that
if you double the size of an animal it
only consumes
two times three-quarters or about a half
one and a half
times as much energy so animals get more
efficient
as they get bigger and they move slower
their heartbeats go down you know
famously an elephant the mouse have
about the same number of heartbeats in a
life etc
so we can say that animal life is
sublinear
but they then moved and captured data
about
cities and discovered that cities are
super linear
at about the level of 1.15 on a lot of
things they measure so if you double the
size
of a city you'll more than double
the size of the number of patents that
come out
you'll also more than double or the
income will go up the average income
will go up as you increase
size but it's also true that the amount
of crime will go up and the amount of
infectious disease like aids will go up
and so cities are super linear in both
the good and the bad
dimensions there's a lot of ground
setting and so what
jordan has proposed in his civilian civ
ium
proposal is to let's see if we can get
the best of both of these two things
which is that
we should basically abandon cities big
big cities
as a modus operandi for human life
because the
super linearities of the bad are just
too strong
and that we should all live in small
scale
communities where we can have really
rich personal relationships that we
could live in great physical beauty
probably a lot like the finned horn
project or what we call proto-b's in the
in the game b world but and here is his
big important butt where he then links
back to
west and bettencourt is that we should
take advantage of the super linearities
on things like science and the arts and
you know every every kind of good thing
by a very intensive networking between
the
smaller cells and of course he doesn't
answer the question how do we do that in
a way that's congruent with humans and
not capturable by marketing
but i think that's a really interesting
you know way to think about it
uh that the city which has gotten us to
where we are today in which
tyson yunkaporta talks about he thinks
cities are bad period
can be gotten rid of with the addition
of networking to small scale living
close to the ground
and mostly self-sufficiently i think
you're definitely
hitting on something there jordan is
hitting on something that there is a
challenge for us to rethink
um from the ground up which is this if
how do we
nest our social environments
in the scale-linking way that we don't
atomize
even further particularly now in in a
kind of pandemic world
where where people like i keep thinking
of the the old roman divide and conquer
thinking somebody's going to find that
very useful that this pandemic is
dividing people and not
allowing for the same amount of of um
human community building
like we had before but with regards to
cities it's
it's a tricky one how do we get from a
to to be because so many people already
live in cities
um yes of course like i just recently
talked to
herbert jira they who spent a long time
studying cities and wrote a book on
regenerative cities creating
regenerative cities in 2000 and
i think it was 14 even and he's part of
the club of rome and part of the
world future council and he in the in
2001 or two he wrote a
schumacher briefing on the ecological
footprint
of the city of london and was looking at
the
footprint of the land that london needed
to meet its needs and and deal with its
wastes and i came up with this very
provocative question what's 149 times
as big as the city of london the land
needs to sustain itself
and so we're talking land that is pretty
much the entire
uk just about supporting one city
obviously that's not sustainable but how
do we make the transition and and i've
kind of
right now it's getting really popular
this sort of odl let's create
regenerative communities and this that
and the other and then sell them at high
property
value to people in costa rica and i i'm
a bit
worried about it's a repeat of the
lifeboat
impulse that also happened in the eco
village movement it's like people
seeing the world's unraveling and saying
i want to create my little
safe haven somewhere and i don't think
like
unless we keep global solidarity in mind
as we
engage in those projects it can be
pretty self-serving
but how do we now that suddenly
it's open again that conversation of
previously everybody's saying
the already half of humanity lives in
cities and by
2050 will we have 70 percent in cities
and then we'll keep growing and
depopulation of the land and all that
but i think that
the pandemic situation is going to make
people
re-question how they want to live but
there is an issue about density
you can't all live in this idyllic
farming environment where you think
where you have hectares to yourself and
your family
so we i think we need to find ways
of bringing new community structures
into the cities
and collaborations between cities and
its regions that's why
for me we haven't paid enough attention
to
re-regionalization and bioregionalism in
this context
um patrick eddis wrote a book in 1910 i
think
um cities and evolution and he made the
point that
a city needs to be planned within the
bioregion that he's that the city is
situated in from the mountains to the
sea
paying attention to the the local river
systems and
all the overlay like he was the the
father of the concept of overlay mapping
that ian mccarthy then
eventually turned into gis and
geographic information system
came from patrick eddis and he said we
need to know the
the soil series we need to know the
fauna and the flora we need to know
geology hydrology everything we need to
we can know about our region and where
our city is standing
and then make our decisions of what to
develop where based on
the integration of all that knowledge
and the the caretaking
of the resource bases that we depend
upon yeah and i think and that's
really important i always emphasize the
bioregional thinking is hugely important
and whether it's uh in terms of having
some diversity within your bioregion
like for instance where our farm is
it's mountainous territory and so you
can actually get some significant
diversity around risk of things like
frost or drought
by just moving a few miles so if we have
an integrated uh
economy at different elevations and in a
couple of different river valleys that
are close together physically
if one area is adversely affected
another one probably isn't so we can get
some diversification
and hence resilience in our little mini
civilization
by paying attention to the details the
real details
of bioregionalism and i think that's
absolutely important
one area where i get a little geeky and
whether it's the
the really sensible path but for some
it's always been something that
fascinated me that projects like the
eden project
in cornwall where they in these domes
recreated ecosystems diverse ecosystems
in a place where they normally don't
exist by just
putting them into a thermal envelope
basically a
very large greenhouse structure i often
wonder is what
with the the wealth of modern technology
and using renewable
energy and and low impact materials
creating thermal flywheels working
in pushing the growing seasons in
certain places a little bit beyond
the normal conditions or even like i
always say that i don't want to live in
a completely localized world because i
like my coffee and i like my hiramate
and so far i haven't seen them growing
on majorca yet
so starting to experiment in different
bioregions
what we can actually grow in a bioregion
i think would be a wonderful
area of innovation and entrepreneurship
the same holds true with the whole
range of integrated vertical farming um
really bringing the best of ecological
design and
aqua culture knowledge into designed
ecosystems that
in an intensive way produce organic
local food
in high density areas and cities i think
i mean there's a lot of
stuff already going on in that space but
i think it's it's something
to pay attention to yeah i've actually
looked into it a fair amount
it doesn't work currently in terms of
actually feeding people at least not
even close
to economically and what it does do the
only thing that you can economically
produce
in urban farming is greens basically
yeah yeah salad greens can be done
economically
but the rest just don't work there's
just too much capital investment per
unit of energy conversion so back to
your topic of you know
is there enough land in some places
there is like for instance the united
states
by my rough calculation we have about 20
hectares
of land call that 22 acres for each
family
and that's enough even if you assume
half of it's not that useful how big is
a family in
in that calculation three people okay so
it works but
it certainly won't work in belgium or uh
even the uk i don't haven't done the
numbers for germany but i'm probably
doesn't work for germany either
there was a reason hitler was looking
for leban's room right
you know many of our highly populated
densely populated countries there's
probably not enough i feel like saying
there was a reason for you for the
ancestors of
um the country that is now called the
united states to come and steal
the land that that country is on yeah
that's true too
are you sure that the nationalistic
pathway of saying oh well
we'd be fine here in america is is is a
pathway towards
actually addressing the the global
issues where we're on or do we
not have to start what i was mentioning
earlier that the solidarity at the
global scale
if you look at ecological footprinting
machonicals work in the footprint
network we've got what 1.68 hectares per
person
of bioproductive land available slightly
different figure
yep yep and you know there's a reason
the u.s
is the saudi arabia of food right
because we have a lot more
good land and decent growing weather
than we actually need
and that was actually my point which is
we don't want a lifeboat theory
where the u.s says or canada or russia
for that matter russia could easily be
very self-sufficient in food if it
wasn't such a screwed up mess
you know these countries should not or
cannot morally take a lifeboat strategy
and say screw everybody else and this is
where
bioregionalism starts to break down
right because we say all right we're
going to organize
mostly bioregionally well it works where
the climate and the land and the soil
and the
population density are right but we've
unfortunately way over
shot it's a goddamn shame that for
historical reasons
we ended up peaking at 10 billion rather
than 2 billion
at 2 billion we could make a lot of
stuff work across the world
but at 8 billion it's going to require
especially if we're going to be moral
and ethical with respect to our global
obligations there's still going to have
to be a shitload of global trade to keep
people from starving to death
yeah i mean the numbers thing there's
more and more research
coming out and like if you if you look
at the impact that the pandemic is
likely to have
all around the world with regard to
people's decision to have children or
not
even if it's for entirely survival
economic reasons because they're in a
depression
i think where we might not even hit the
10 10 billion that were predicted we
might
actually turn the curve i mean still a
lot of people putting a lot of pressure
on the planet i
agree with that statement absolutely but
but i i think that
the likelihood that we will see
a peak around 20 30 20 35
and then a continuing decline of um
human population
is relatively high that would be great
now the
big question is africa the rest of the
world is clearly on the trend but for
whatever reason
africa seems to be resisting the trend
that as
education and economics improve
family sizes go down now they have
certainly gone down in africa but it's
on a very different curve than in the
rest of the world
and truthfully most of the rest of the
growth through the century
in the demographic projections have to
do with africa
so you know if africa gets more strongly
influenced by the
curves the rest of the world has been on
then then perhaps you're correct but if
not
probably not yep that's the thing about
futures we'll
we'll see when we get there as yogi
berra said making predictions is
difficult particularly about the future
right but we have to do it let's go on
to our next topic
so one that we uh hinted around in the
first conversation and we were teasing
each other we never really got into it
and that
is consciousness right i think we both
wanted to talk about consciousness
we didn't have time now consciousness is
my favorite topic it's what i've spent
probably more time thinking about
reading
writing software writing a hundred pages
worth of rough material
for a review article since 2014.
and you always have to start is what is
it right when someone says consciousness
it's a very slippery word
and you know i think of it as
what it's like to be an animal inside
the experience
of a movie of your own life right you
know that that's what
i think of as consciousness and i follow
as the closest models not very
elaborated but john searle the
philosopher from berkeley
one of the leading philosophers of mind
who's also studied the
cognitive science he has a point of view
he calls biological naturalism
which essentially derives from a very
careful analysis of some of the classic
problems of theory of mind and others uh
that
consciousness is a purely biological
function only found in animals
found in all advanced animals and
that's basically it there's nothing
magic about it and we don't
our understanding of how it arises is
still
not complete by any means but he finds
no
reason to believe that it's anything
other than a biological
system in fact his well-known statement
about it
is that consciousness is like digestion
they're both systems that do something
they have many different parts to them
you can't point at
something and say this is consciousness
in the same way you can't point at
something in the body and say that's the
digestion
and they both are operate at high
energetic and genetic costs
to keep them operating and that's really
the it simplifies tremendously the
thinking
about consciousness and i add the rut
corollary and searle says
consciousness is like digestion and i
say it often produces the same end
result
yeah yeah back to our conversation about
night soil
so anyway i would also add at least my
view on consciousness
is gerald edelman while i disagree with
some of gerald edelman's
analysis of consciousness i think his
distinction
uh that he makes between primary
consciousness and extended consciousness
is hugely important
he would say that the consciousness of a
dog or
a uh even a reptile is
continuous with human consciousness in
that those animals live within a movie
of their own
life essentially and a censorium of
the various senses that op feels like
you're in it in real time
but what they what they all lack minus
perhaps a couple of the highest
animals like elephants whales and great
apes
is any ability to self-reflect
to use probably symbolic means to be
able to tell a story about themselves
and that's what he calls extended
consciousness and you know i argue that
while we do see a little bit of that in
elephants
great apes and perhaps whales it's only
a teeny bit and it's really a pretty
bright line
between humans something happened
between chimps and humans
that ratcheted us up to a whole new
level of
consciousness probably having to do with
our ability to manipulate
symbols so what's your theory of
consciousness or at least your
description of consciousness
before we get down to more discussion
about what it all means well you know
make sure we're sort of on the same page
or or at least if we're on different
pages
we know what those two pages are yeah i
i sense we're possibly on two different
pages in the
sense that what i heard you describe or
the quote you
read out to me is bumping into
the limitations of what happens if you
create that
keyboard and you start with the lower
notes only like if you start with the
assumption that
life and consciousness emerges out of
dead matter
then that's what you get but ken wilber
and alan combs
wrote the paper together in 2010 which i
quote a
piece of in in my book and i just found
the
the quote and it's worth reading because
that sort of describes
in my limited perspective i am not
in any way saying that i can give that
answer
alan wrote a wonderful book called
consciousness explained better
which for me is one of the the clearer
descriptions of the complexity that that
we
we have to deal with when we look at
consciousness but this
quote starts like this consciousness is
much more
than an evolutionary accident or
epiphenomenon to biochemical processes
in our head consciousness is in fact
fundamentally woven into the
universe itself we are saying that it is
that some degree of subjectivity
is indeed present all the way up and all
the way down
in the evolutionary ladder from the
tiniest quark to the biggest brains
this consciousness can be loosely
described as a perspective making
perspective taking system that creates
collects organizes deeper wider and more
sophisticated points of view
as it develops and for me that saying
we will never know what a
emperor penguin penguin really feels
when
that first ray of sun hits the
colony while they've been standing in
the ice balancing the eggs on their on
their
flippers we won't know what it feels
like to
a sequoia tree to be free of snow and
feel
the warmth of the spring sunshine
but these beings take
a relational perspective to the larger
hole
that has brought them forth and are
sentient and there's lots of
scientific based research on the
sentience of of plants
that is coming out out of spain and out
of italy in a number of places
at the moment so i know i was originally
a
um ethologist a behavioral biologist
looking at
um barriers of marine mammals elephant
seals whales and dolphins and
also a little bit of primatology and of
course it's nothing like
the consciousness that you're referring
to in human beings but that doesn't mean
that there isn't
an immediate sense making that is
along the lines of maturama and varela's
santiago theory of
cognition that you don't even need a
brain or
neuro circuits to have that
initial structural coupling of defining
yourself as self
like making the first distinction that
distinguishes
whatever that perspective making is with
regard to the environment that has
just been created through the act of
perspective making
and and that's a very very different
view of consciousness and
um and again like we can we could now
look back to the earlier conversation of
saying is it scientific because in
the world you you were sort of standing
more firmly on
you were saying that the vedanta and
taoism um
don't really qualify as sciences but
when you look at how their perspective
on consciousness
corroborates a lot of the research that
is actually being done
within the confines of western science
i think there's some something to
explore there
yeah there are things that are certainly
stimulating to the ideas let me uh give
an alternative way
and again unfortunately a stand word
consciousness is used
in for so many different things it's
really hard to have a precise
conversation about it
you know uh certainly i agree that
many kinds of of matter even before life
and certainly all forms of life
do respond to their environments and in
what you'd call
with competence i guess is the word i
would like to use and the language we
use
at the santa fe institute is we call
those complex adaptive
systems and frankly there's even complex
adaptive systems
in nature uh pre-life you know you know
sand piles
or the way asteroids kind of manipulate
themselves in their orbits based on
sunlight and comets and so it's simple
but
they're complex and they're adaptive
relatively and certainly a
sequoia tree is very complex adaptive
system
and when the snow melts and the sun sun
comes out
all kinds of different things are
happening in that tree
but i would argue that you know
something's going on there there's
communications going on as we know with
the mycelium with other trees not just
the same species but multiple species
interactions with the nature of the soil
some of it on real time basis some of it
lower than real time
but i would push back and say there's no
movie going on there's no
being embedded in a real-time sense of
being and that is a very specific
technology that that evolution developed
and here's the interesting thing about
in fact a book i would strongly
recommend to people interested in this
question
it's called the ancient origins of
consciousness how the brain created
experience by todd
feinberg and john mallett and they
really get down to this biological
naturalism perspective in a very serious
way
and look at it in terms of evolution and
they argue
that again for the fact that
consciousness and this
sense of being in a movie that you can
then at the human level
be self-aware of goes way back at least
to the
reptiles probably to the amphibians but
maybe no
no further back than that and that you
know the the
primary consciousness in the edelman
speak has more or less
just continuously evolved and gotten
better and different you know for
instance our dog
has a much better consciousness of smell
than we do
while we have a a better consciousness
of vision
for instance and a hawk has better
consciousness of vision than we do
but no consciousness of smell at all and
then to you know follow thomas nagel and
his
work on what's it like to be a bat bat
has echolocation and whole sensorium
that we can't even understand right
but anyway those things we can actually
look at their evolution
and they are different than
the state of being of even life
prior to that like a sponge does not
have
anything like being in a movie now
here's another
thing that i just found amazing in this
book they posit and provide some
evidence for the fact
that this this idea of consciousness as
being in a movie
actually evolved at least twice once
from the amphibian
reptile to mammals and birds but a
second time and they make a pretty
strong argument that they're not
connected because there was a big
evolutionary gap
encephalopods meaning octopi and some of
the larger squid
octopi in particular show an awful lot
of signs of being conscious
even though they're not related there
was a big big gap between these two
trees of consciousness
so it may indeed say that there is
a tendency to find consciousness in the
evolution of life like
but there is still a pretty clear line
between
those consciousnesses even if they
evolve separately
in the prior world of complex adaptive
systems
well yeah it's it's tricky to build
on the conversation because it because
it it's just one particular lens into
consciousness that that i personally
find
difficult to connect with because
the true participatory consciousness
that also
draws like pays attention to how we
bring forth the world based on
the modes of explanation we use
isn't isn't really acknowledged in in
that to my mind
what i'm trying to get it is like the
the word that uh
the work that henry bortoff has done um
based on
gertie and phenomenology he writes like
i've just found
as you were speaking i found this quote
that that again points to
where i'm coming from the fundamental
discovery on
um on which phenomenology is based is
that consciousness has a
structure of intentionality it would be
better to say that consciousness is
intentionality
this is often expressed by saying that
consciousness is always conscious of
something in other words consciousness
is always directed towards an object
hence in cognitive perception there's an
in
the soluble unity between the conscious
mind and the object
of which it is conscious and that means
that if we think of the world
in the in terms of solid objects and
atoms
and matter then we bring forth a
different
connection to that world than if we have
a truly participatory consciousness
of entertaining that we are reflections
of
that world through the act of
perspective taking
i don't think there's any disagreement
there actually in fact john searle
wrote a very good book called
intentional he also wrote a great book
called mind a brief introduction
which talks about how consciousness and
intentionality are utterly interwoven
right and that you really can't think
about consciousness without also
thinking about intentionality in our
relationship between the subjective and
the objective
and i don't see any conflict there
actually which is quite interesting
which is which gets me to the second
usage of the word consciousness and
maybe here is where we get
into more agreement or at least we find
more interesting disagreements
you know particularly in things like
integral and
buddhism etc they use consciousness in a
different way
as well which is not about are you in a
movie of
the experience of your life and
interacting intentionally with the
objects in that movie
but rather kind of a level of perception
thing and some of this goes into
developmental psychology as well you
know when we're
when we're small we're very egocentric
and then we start to have a relationship
with
our mother and then to our family and
then our community
and then as we grow older probably our
tribe or our culture
and then some people uh achieve what's
often called a global level of
consciousness where they
are able to actually think about the
world as a whole and some people claim i
don't know if they can really get their
universal consciousness where they can
think in terms of the whole universe
and certainly that kind of development
psychological development happens in
humans
and if we want to call that
consciousness that may be a little bit
closer
to some of the concerns that you were
just expressing
yeah i mean definitely that i i find
the wilbur combs matrix of levels and
states of consciousness
quite a useful map of how we've in
different ways talked about
consciousness and and the evolution of
consciousness
but it also has the the danger as
has happened a lot in the integral
community is that people get kind of a
little bit too tied up
in the nomenclature that they've then
developed um or
whether it's an integral or in spiral
dynamics is
similar people just confuse the
map with the territory a little bit but
for me that
dynamic map is useful because it allows
for like it has a research basis
based on all these questionnaires that
graves did in in the
distant past i think in the in the 50s
and 60s
of the different value meme clusters
that people take towards the world
and how they then also define what what
friday of couple called
a crisis of perception a lot of it is
this
how do we define self and world that
relates into how we then
perceive the world and i i think that's
also what
where where that that whole issue
between the east and the west
or western signs versus vedic
wisdom or taoism then all those
buddhism they've paid a lot of attention
in
basically experiential phenomenological
studies
to consciousness and and it's very
very tricky to put that in parallel to a
analytical consciousness as explained
within western science
henry bortoff described it as a holistic
mode of consciousness that is
complementary um to the analytical one
but but but not necessarily
commensurable yeah we'll see i mean uh
there is a
rapidly growing western science of
consciousness and it's very interesting
i know some of the more serious
scientists in that realm and most of
them are very interested in and
are practitioners of eastern traditions
right
and so they uh sam harris being one
well-known one
but there are plenty of others and so
yeah i don't think that they're
contradictory but i do suspect that if
the cognitive science of consciousness
continues
we may well actually be able to explain
the phenomenology
even of a holistic perspective
from a cognitive neuroscience point of
view yeah
that's what i mean that that the
keyboard is continuous that like we
normally do find
um these areas of overlap where suddenly
without
breaking any of the axioms or rules and
methodologies
of the wonderful tool that is and and
valuable tool that is western
science then suddenly pushes into
areas that describe in their language
something that other
i would still call them sciences have
described sometimes millennia ago
in a different language this is
interesting because this is this is what
has to happen somehow because
i'm more and more convinced that there
is no real argument here there's sort of
an entanglement with words
and i don't really feel like i've gotten
all the way through because obviously i
come from
initially a very extreme materialist
realist perspective
as i've learned more about consciousness
and have done some dabbling in the
other ways of thinking i can sort of
feel that somehow they're the same thing
but that
uh synthesis has not yet uh been done
but now to bring us back to sort of
where we were trying to get to earlier
which is this how the human has to be
upgraded
probably to achieve uh regenerative
culture
before we go there just briefly because
it kind of makes the link to where
you're going now
um well okay you know that batson
famously said the biggest problem
for of humanity come from the difference
in the way that humans think in the way
that nature like more than
more than human nature thinks and he
also pointed towards this
misunderstanding of mind and and
um just want to read one more henry
voter quote where
who's really the person who when i met
him at schumacher college in 2001 when
he was teaching
gertie and science and this
phenomenological holistic consciousness
approach to us but not
in a theoretical way but through
exercises and pretty intense work
i ended up after five days of visit from
this guy i ended up having the worst
migraine of my life and for 48 hours was
literally under a blanket
feeling like my synapses were rewiring
themselves
one of the most influential teachings
i've ever sort of
and and mentors i've had and henry
writes
we miss the dimension of mind
which is active in our lives the
dimension of mind
in cognitive perception is as invisible
to us
to begin with as the movement of the
earth
just as it seems so evident to us that
everything we see about us
is just there i.e objects instead of
meaning
and that cognitive perception is just
sense perception
we are accustomed to thinking of mind as
if it were inside of us in our heads but
it is the other way around
we live within a dimension of mind which
is for the most part as invisible to us
as the air we breathe we usually only
discover it when it breaks down
i think that speaks to that shift in
perspective
of of um maybe consciousness is primary
and matter evolves out of consciousness
yeah i would reject that but that's a
two-hour conversation right there but we
put it on the table
but i will agree with the fact that you
know we
are not our mind consciousness is a
relatively small
specialized sub-function of the mind in
fact those of us who have had things
like ego death experiences
know that you can be alive and walking
around in the world without any eye
right and so the mind is way way deeper
than the ego
and you know most of the mind most of
the brain at least
is spent on lower level things like
processing perception keeping your heart
beating etc
and the uh you know the part that
supports
consciousness is maybe 20 of the brain
and but it utterly relies upon that
iceberg beneath the surface and even the
part that is
involved with creating consciousness we
have no ability to see into it
we only experience this higher realm of
consciousness
we have no idea what the working parts
are going on underneath unless we work
very very very very hard which i think
is quite interesting
but back to this where i was uh heading
to go which is that
i think yourself for sure and lots of
other people and increasingly myself
have come around to the view that
raising
consciousness away above the ego and the
tribe
to the global and the planetary and in a
more holistic fashion
is going to be part of helping humans
organize themselves so as to be able to
reach a regenerative culture
yes and yeah in the sense that
i definitely fall into that category of
still
somehow believing that that will make a
big difference
and at the same time i'm not quite sure
whether
the view that we just need to get
everybody to agree and understand this
and then everything will be fine
is is probably a bit limited as well
like coming back to the the world of
homes
matrix and and these the kind of map of
different world views
i think we need to have the whole whole
spectrum open all the time because there
will always be
people moving through that developmental
spectrum
and and so we need to find a narrative
that speaks to people
at all the different levels of
consciousness and still
includes the meta narrative
that is say saying like okay it's
wonderful let's
acknowledge that all our disagreements
of perspective
are part of biodiversity they're
wonderful that's where the creativity of
our species comes from that we have
different points of view
and we're now at a point where there's
so many of us
on a planet with a life support system
that we have
put in jeopardy that we need to agree on
some
basic commonalities with regard to not
infringing on ecosystems and planetary
health and
actively working towards repairing
ecosystems and planetary health
and and that's that's what we need to do
i don't think we're going to get
everybody to agree with us and
suddenly move from kind of egocentric to
tribal centric and
to to nation-centric and then on to
planetary consciousness and cosmic
consciousness
we don't have necessary time for
achieving that
yeah i don't think we have any
disagreement there you know i think i
was speaking in the most general of
terms but i am
very strong about the fact that we have
to acknowledge high diversity in humans
in many dimensions from
pure cognitive ability to values to how
they
address issues that we would call
spirituality etc
and that any attempt to squash out that
uh diversity
is exceedingly dangerous and results in
horror shows like nazism or marxist
leninism
and in fact the words i've created to
express that concept is coherent
pluralism uh there's some things that it
is important that we agree about like
for instance we live in a limited world
at least at our current level of
technology
and that if we exceed the limits bad
things are going to happen but on the
other hand
we have to leave room for lots of ways
for people to be
people and evolve cultures that live
within those limits
and in terms of the idea that not
everyone is going to be at the same
level that's also obviously true
and a thinker i've i've recently become
very interested in
he goes it's actually a two people
writing team
called hanzi frank that's a pseudonym
and they write a whole lot about
the fact that people are going to be at
different levels and they and they make
some distinctions which i find very
useful between
hierarchical complexity which you can
sort of think about as
iq ish but then he also adds the very
important concept of
code which is the the details of the
social operating system
and then they talk about state which are
the ability to reach these higher
consciousnesses
which will vary by people and then depth
which is what are the range of these
states that a person has experienced in
these
lives and they say we have to realize
that people are going to vary on all
four of these dimensions
but we can work towards moving humanity
up in all four dimensions as a way to
get ourselves ready
for essentially a regenerative culture
i'm familiar with
their framework and i i didn't know
until just now that behind hansi frein
after
two people rather than one person and
that it was a pseudonym
but it reminds me a little bit of
wilbur's um lines of development and i
i've
certainly realized that a lot in in kind
of collaborative projects and so on that
there is a distinction between um that
kind of what will we call the cognitive
line like thinking yourself into
enlightenment and this this higher level
of consciousness and
and all its benefits and then actually
having that also in your um fully
embodied um kinesthetic development line
or
in your like in your somatosexual line
or your
your spiritual development line so they
it's it's just
um slightly different areas of our
personality
and that sometimes we we can just throw
this grappling hook
way ahead and pull us with the cognitive
line towards
um areas that that we haven't fully
integrated in
in the whole human being sense and
that's
that's where i personally and this might
be a complete like my own
my own story and my own limitations here
i i sometimes find
there comes a point when it gets too
analytical and too mappy
and too um how do we
create the process that everybody can
evolve faster
that that i i just recoil
because i kind of appreciate the chaos
the not knowing
the confusion the the clarity
and how they alternate and um
and the the kind of intellectual
cognitive sense making
but then also really giving value to
just
sitting with a question in a beautiful
spot in nature and
trusting the answer that comes without
any
doubting from a sort of analytical or
where
with whether that just come from like
really working with intuition
and embodied sensing and feeling um in a
way that that i
it informs my work i can't pretend it
doesn't
and um there are points where despite
all the analytical training and
two degrees in science and a degree in
design i prefer to stay fuzzy and i
prefer to stay
multifaceted so i think that's right
right and when
even in uh you know again cognitive
science we know from work
by antonio damasio that almost all of
our actual decisions are based on
emotion
right we we build these great cosmic
frameworks right but at the end of the
day
something deep underneath which we don't
even understand is the one that
tilts the needle to our actual decisions
you know and hence
i think the merit of jordan hall's
scivium idea
let's make sure we're situated in
beautiful
supportive low risk or at least low risk
of starving
places so that our emotions are not
over amped and not overexposed to mass
media and advertising etc and then i do
believe that our
you know organic bodies are pretty damn
good at making good decisions
yeah i mean what jordan is sort of
recreating with this vision
is a bit like the buddhist notions of
the buddha the dharma and the sangha
um like basically the sangha is the
community that keeps you on the path
the the dharma is the developmental
impulse like how do we
grow individual consciousness and
community consciousness at the same time
and the buddha is nothing but that
people can do this and that there are
people who have done it before that we
can
refer to to basically feel like it's not
a futile
exercise to to get to these states do
you think that that's that's somewhat
related i truthfully hadn't made that
connection but now that you mention it i
do see it i'm gonna have to think about
that a little bit
right we're getting late on time here
it's been a wonderful conversation and
even though it's part two
i'm gonna skip over a few things and
because i am also with you strongly that
we can't overthink this we got to do
stuff right time is marching on if we
don't solve these problems
uh the meta crisis as we call it in game
b by 2100
yes planet earth and life will keep
marching on but
life for homo sapiens will not be good
and that merely raising people's
consciousness ain't enough
no absolutely not that but that's that's
why like now remember
something that you said earlier when you
mentioned jordan's work that i wanted to
pick up on which is a dynamic that i
think we find
more and more is that at the level what
you were saying like and then these
communities need to connect and
and work together this this like how
much energy do we put
into re-patterning our entire way
not just of thinking and doing things
but our entire way of
being with this world and with each
other um
at the local and regional scale which
is a very personal development bit in
one way but then it becomes a very kind
of skilled
social facilitation of multi-stakeholder
processes and
and the and the frustrating complexity
of working with the real world
when you when you have to talk to
planners and and local authority and and
local business and local schools and
whatever to engage everybody in
redesigning the human impact on their
particular piece
of the world and their bio region their
community
and then how do we engage in resourcing
and networking
this process and reflecting on how do we
do this
in each bioregion together and connect
all the other good people that are
popping up everywhere around the world
in intending
to start this bioregional journey and
and i
i have seen certainly in the networks
that i'm moving is
a sort of tension between how much
energy to put where
and and that one of the biggest
exercises we where i guess we all need
to
um do is is where to put our energies
um and and what to prioritize and um
in my life i i feel like i've spent
a few too many hours on webinars
podcasts social media and all of that
connecting and learning and and weaving
new web works of meaning with with
wonderful people like yourself
but i since my book came out in 2016
have noticed a little bit of
a distraction through all that away
from a process that i started 10 years
ago
of really wanting to grow
deep roots in this bio region the island
of mallorca that i
chose as my my home and and engage with
the networks that are analog in front of
my eyes
real people real community real
ecosystems and
and and begin that transition and in
where i'm at right now in my personal
life
i feel like i need to refocus from what
has
points been 80 global focus to 20
local focus to to actually flip that
balance around
um but that then means being very
good at saying no to the possibility of
all that global net networking and
finding the
the real valuable um opportunities
to to yet still engage in that because
it is vitally important
where do you sit with with in your life
with that
balance of doing your wonderful series
of podcasts
and and weaving the game b community
and then actually still having the time
that that you
you work with your local community and
your farm and and
the the people you meet at the the local
store and so on
i think it's a fairly similar journey to
yours tell you the truth
one thing i have done which i actually
have been doing for a few years but i
did more rigorously this year is i'm
currently on a six-month
social media sabbatical no social media
no twitter no facebook
no well and i've been doing that for
facebook for four years
and you know we can spend just way too
much time
on those social media both wallowing in
other people's
ideas and promoting our own and so
having uh gone on that break
in july has opened me up first of july
has opened up a lot of
thinking about just these questions that
you ask uh
and like you i have been feeling that
i've been doing this
work in one form or another game b and
its predecessor
since 2012 and i think
i'm done about as much theoretical and
work as i'm capable of i'm more of a
person of action
and very much feel that the time has
come
to put up or shut up on our ideas and
actually create some functioning
communities
uh in the game b world we call these
bees
and they actually mean building it on
the ground making it work
we talk about you know
psychotechnologies which which could
include meditation
it could include ecstatic dance could
include
breath work could include psychedelic
drugs could include include
electrical implants right and that uh
you know creating a set of psycho
technologies
for each proto-b uh is a
curatorial function and it probably
varies by the people that are in the
proto-b
so anyway i am feeling the strong urge
to
help catalyze other people to create a
couple of proto-b's and possibly even to
be the driving force behind one of them
because
i'm a feared that time is short and if
we don't if we can't at least begin to
experiment with
real communities on the ground which
were designed from day one to live
within their
environmental limits uh or at least
close then one of the things
like we do talk about in the proto-b
discussion
is that the first proto-b's will not
actually be living within their limits
right that we
we're not going to make our own computer
chips for instance and there ain't
nothing we can do about intel
and what bad things they do to create
computer chips and
there'll be plenty of other examples
like that but we can be aware of the gap
between true regenerative and
sustainable living on a proto-b
at any given point in time and the goal
of getting to the point where it really
is
sustainable and regenerative a
regenerative part we can work
and work hard i think there's a lot of
good knowledge i think i mentioned last
time
on our farm my wife and i have we have
built soil we have tripled the
capacity to grow hay without using any
artificial fertilizer we've done
sustainable logging
we've done major repair on the water
courses the streams that run
through our area we built ponds to you
know keep water from running off too
quickly
so there's a lot of things we know and a
lot of people know more about this than
i
in terms of regeneration of a local
piece of soil and i think that's also
got to be
literally put to work but embedded in a
matrix
that can exist within game a and this is
we call
how do we design the proto-b so that it
can parasitize game a right so
in a game b community you have many
people working the land and making
furniture and making clothes
even but probably you have other people
doing uh
you know management consulting and
programming
to pull some resources in to make the
produ be
actually viable in the world so this is
where my heart is at and i think if the
pandemic hadn't occurred at least one
proto-b would have been launched in 2020
but i believe that the pandemic has
pushed us out probably a year
and so i'll be damned disappointed if by
the end of 2021
at least one or two proto-b's haven't
actually started to emerge upon the face
of the earth
this sounds wonderful and it makes me
feel good because of my past with
um having hung out and worked with and
explored and visited
so many of the um communities in the
global eco village network
the days are sort of reinventing the
wheel but of course in a complete
different
new context with different people with a
different set of skills and tools
but there is a lot of learning that as
you set out to create these proto-b's
there's a lot of learning
from the world of intentional
communities in the world of
equal villages because they it's very
often that people come into these
four dimensions of such community
projects um social ecological worldview
and economic and seem to sort of
focus it on one or the other and and
particularly the social dimension how
people
create visions together make decisions
all of that is
is really complex and and i think we
we should as there seems to be such a
drive at the moment to create these sort
of
proto-b's i think it's important to to
pick up the learnings that that we've
already made
and also i think another conceptual
thing that there's a is actually a
lesson from the eco village movement is
that
what happens naturally as you create a
sort of in bucky fuller's terms let's
build a new system that makes the old
system obsolete if you do that at the
community scale in a real physical place
the amount of work it takes to do that
well
focuses in tension of everybody engaged
in that pro project
relatively inwardly to build up the
basic infrastructure to create
the like make sure that it's zero impact
and that it has all the renewables this
that and the other and the green
building and whatnot
and in that process it's very quickly
building a bubble that isn't fully
grounded in the nested system that it
sits in
and it like just not out of spite not
enough because people don't want to
talk to the local rednecks that live
next door
but because they just don't have time
and the the key bit
is if you if these proto-b's are going
to be successful you have to from the
beginning think of them
in a scale-linking design way and say
how do we make this proto-b
interact with the wider bioregional
context it sits in
and how do we make it into the the
yogurt culture that turns the milk
of the region into yogurt um if if you
don't
have that process from the beginning to
my mind they're just going to be
a recreating of the ecovillage
experiments of the 1960s and 70s and
80s and so on yeah i think you're 100
right unfortunately
uh the game b code we call deep code
includes all those things right it has
to be scalable over time
through copying and what we call x in a
box where we share
our techniques we strongly believe that
as we i said earlier proto-b's can't be
self-sufficient
and they have to be thoughtful about how
they engage the world and i've also
wrote my paper on
proto-b's called a journey to game b at
the more mundane level as you said the
proto-b's should participate in the
community
uh football league right they should
become members of the
local volunteer fire department you know
they should be
and should even engage in local politics
you know currently game b
is choose national politics as this
complete show
but uh we believe that that we should be
active involved in local politics
and so i think we definitely want to
avoid the uh
you know the fallacies of the past and
fortunately people helped know a lot
more about
those previous experiences than i do in
the game b world and
are bringing their perspectives to bear
but i think your sense is exactly right
that it can easily
become too hobbyist essentially in
trying to micro-optimize
something which is not ready for
micro-optimization yet
and that we have to be understand that
we're a teeny little piece in a much
bigger
system even though it is our long-term
goal to convert the system
to the new cause but that's not going to
happen overnight so i think
all very good thoughts and i hopefully
will inform
the formations of uh the various
proto-b's which i hope will come in the
world over the next
few years have you um had a conversation
with pedro tarak yet
uh no don't know that name pedro tarak
is a lawyer from argentina who is a
wonderful man i'll um
send you the link to a conversation i
had with him recently and he set up
with a number of other people he always
is very keen to point out that he
doesn't have nothing himself he always
works with in collaboration and in
networks
which is why i mention him um he he set
up
sistema bay in latin america which is a
decentralized network of many local
chapters
and there are b lawyers the b
universities sued others can be
um so and it's basically about systems
transformation
and it's exploring that in in in
different areas
and um he's a wonderful wonderful man
um deeply uh sound individual who's
really walked his talk ever since a
childhood or a youth in the
dictatorship in in argentina
and um i think you'd have a wonderful
conversation with him
ah look forward to it i love uh love
chatting with new folks it's interesting
that he uses the bee
terminology right in this case it came
from
more from an entrepreneurial perspective
that he was together with some people in
chile and other pla parts of latin
america
looking at how companies were trying to
become for purpose companies and and
socially transforming companies or
environmentally
restoring or regenerating companies and
and just when they were saying there's
something happening there's a trend we
need to
create a latin american network of these
kind of companies
they both are the the key founders of
systemabe found out about
b corps in in the the b lab in the u.s
and while of course they're much
shallower
as as a system within the corporate
environment and the whole certification
games we don't need to get into but
pedro and his friends basically said we
want to
include that but in a wider context
because it's not just about business
it's about
all forms of leadership across society
in all walks of life
and and that's what he's been working on
and it's um he's also on the
well-being economy alliance network
you'd have a
bowl of a conversation with him he's a
great guy yeah
look forward to it in fact i recently
had a wonderful conversation on the
podcast with michelle
bauwens about the wider the much wider
opportunity to do
creative things than just b corpse right
there's so many
wonderful ways to build cooperation
but it does require some knowledge of
the law and how to you know how to
use organizations for human good not
just as profit maximizing engines
well i think on that note we're going to
wrap up uh we've run over our time
that's okay
as always an incredibly stimulating and
interesting conversation
well thank you so much i'm amazed i woke
up i'm dripping with sweat here in the
heat wave but
i certainly woke up and and i always
enjoy the way that you hold
different perspectives on your show and
and you like it's it's it's great
because i know we can
micro areas disagree and still come up
with a wonderful conversation that
hopefully
adds value to everybody listening so
thank you so much for inviting me again
yeah indeed in fact one of our game b
co-founders bruce kunkel has
a line that i think summarizes that
thought very well which he calls
alignment beyond agreement
we certainly have that and i look
forward to the protobeast
appearing and maybe i'm in in a
different language but i'm
working on focusing my attention on the
pro to be here in mallorca
so yeah i'd love to when you at some
point have you back on the show and talk
about what you're doing
great wonderful have a wonderful rest of
the day and
thanks again for inviting me yes thanks
production services and audio editing by
jared james consulting
music by tom muller at modern